MAXENCE CERFONTAINE

Cloud Architecture Engineer | Paris | +33695844554 | maxence.cerfontaine@outlook.fr | Profil Linkedin

PROFILE

Graduated with a Master's degree specializing in cloud architecture from EFREI Paris, I am currently a cloud engineer at Hardis Group, where I am gaining experience primarily on AWS, and to a lesser extent on Azure and GCP. I leverage my skills in both designing and implementing cloud solutions while optimizing infrastructure costs.

EXPERIENCE

Hardis Group

Cloud Engineer | Paris La Défense, France

Mar 2024 – Present

Responsibilities within the Cloud Operations team:

- Participating in cloud projects on AWS, validating technical solutions, designing, and build solutions for our partners in diverse industries such as FitnessPark, Finaré, and Dimotrans.
- Setting up a data platform to manage internal business applications data for Finaré and deploy the infrastructure on AWS using IaC CloudFormation scripts.
- Creating action plans in the form of small projects to continuously transform infrastructures.
- Integrating FinOps practices to optimize infrastructure costs, particularly through a start-and-stop feature using CloudFormation.
- Providing support and managing incidents for our various clients' infrastructures via a ITSM ticketing tool.
- Enhancing skills primarily in AWS, as well as GCP and Azure to a lesser extent, and in IaC using CloudFormation and Terraform.

Fitness Park – via Hardis Group

Cloud Engineer | Paris, France

Mar 2024 – present

- Involved in the refactoring of the Terraform codebase to clean up infrastructure drifts and re-establish the automatic deployment CI pipeline
- Delivered new site deployments and continuous improvement projects using Terraform
- Deployed a new application for Fitness Park ("Égérie") over a 1-month project:
 - Defined project scope and designed architecture (including infrastructure diagram and cost estimation)
 - O Deployed the application on a new, fully isolated stack, independent from the existing infrastructure

Dimotrans - via Hardis Group

Cloud Engineer | Paris La Défense, France

Mar 2024 – Dec 2024

- Operations and monitoring of AWS infrastructure (RUN) audit and recommendations
- Migration of legacy databases to more recent versions
- Infrastructure management through an ITSM tool (iTop) and support handling via ticketing system

Finaré – via Hardis Group

Cloud Architect - SRE | Paris, France

May 2024 - Sep 2024

- Designed the full AWS architecture for a data platform project integrating AWS and Snowflake
- Deployed all resources using Infrastructure as Code with AWS CloudFormation
- Managed network configuration, IAM users, and monitoring setup following AWS best practices

DataHippique - Graduation Project

PMU France | Efrei Paris

Dec 2023 - Jan 2024

Graduation project in partnership between EFREI Paris and PMU France.

- Studied and designed a cloud architecture for a project involving horse racing data from across Europe. The main goal was to offer the IT team a fresh perspective on the current architecture and identify optimization opportunities.
- Delivered a full architecture diagram, based on a serverless approach using managed AWS services such as Lambda (to run Python scripts), Glue (for ETL), and S3 (for data storage).

FORMATION

Master Cloud Architecture

EFREI Paris School of Engineering | Paris, France

2022 - 2024

Academic Semester Abroad (English courses)

Concordia University | Montréal, Canada

Jan 2022 – May 2022

Bachelor's Degree of Engineering Science - BioInformatics minor

EFREI Paris School of Engineering | Paris, France

2019-2022

SKILLS

- Cloud Providers: AWS (Advanced), Azure (Fundamentals), GCP (Fundamentals)
- Infrastructure as Code: CloudFormation, Terraform
- Langage de programmation : Python
- Soft Skills: Open-minded, curious, creative, team player, enthusiastic, attentive
- Languages: French (Native), English (Advanced)

CERTIFICATIONS

- AWS Certified: Cloud Solution Architect Associate
- AWS Certified : Cloud Practitioner
- Microsoft AZ-104
- Microsoft AZ-900
- Microsoft MS-900
- Projet Voltaire: 815/1000 (RWVVP43)
- TOEIC: 930/990

REFERENCES

Sylvain Chabi

Principal Cloud Architect | AWS Certified Instructor Champion | Linkedin